Guide to the Alois M. Nagler Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alois M. Nagler papers
1932-1973
MS 1921
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(3 boxes)
The papers comprise correspondence, topical files, writings, and teaching materials documenting the career of Alois M. Nagler as theater historian, teacher, and author.
Nagler, A. M. (Alois Maria), 1907-1993
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale School of Drama, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Alois Maria Nagler was born in Graz, Austria, in 1907, and educated at the University of Graz. In the 1930s he was a theater critic and literary editor for a Viennese newspaper. Nagler visited the United States as a guest lecturer in the late 1930s and did not return to Europe. In 1946 he joined the Yale faculty teaching theater history and was director of graduate studies in theater history until his retirement in 1976. Nagler was co-founder and past president of the International Federation for Theatre Research (IFTR) and co-founder and former chairman of the American Society for Theatre Research (ASTR). He is the author of A Source Book in Theatrical History. Nagler died in Wallingford, Connecticut, on August 5, 2008.
Scope and Contents
The papers comprise correspondence, topical files, writings, and teaching materials documenting the career of Alois M. Nagler as theater historian, teacher, and author.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by type of material.
Theater historians; Theater -- History; Nagler, A. M. (Alois Maria), 1907-1993; Yale University -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1932-1969 (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
- Topical files
  - American Society for Theatre Research (ASTR) correspondence and organizational materials, 1958-1969 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - Blevins, Davis, Rhapsody, correspondence, drafts, and other materials, circa 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13-15)
    Scope and Contents
    Rhapsody was an operetta by Blevins based on a story by Nagler.
  - Encyclopedia Britannica correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Federation for Theatre Research (IFTR) correspondence and organizational materials, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
- Writings
  - Odéon, Théâtre de France, 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Shakespeare und seine Bühne, circa 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Viennese caprice, circa 1952-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Theatre festivals of the Medici, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Le tout Paris des premiéres, circa 1952-1972 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Unsorted, circa 1952-1972 (Box 2, Folder 3-17)
- Yale files
  - D.F.A. plans, 1950-1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Exams and quizzes, 1952-1972 (Box 2, Folder 19-21)
  - Teaching materials, notes for drama seminar 136, circa 1952-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Theater collection, 1941-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3-5)